<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><news-list><channel><title><![CDATA[Code Of Honor]]></title><description><![CDATA[Game design, programming and more]]></description><link><![CDATA[http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog]]></link><language><![CDATA[en-US]]></language><item><title><![CDATA[Stay Awhile and Listen]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/stay-awhile-and-listen]]></link><pubDate><![CDATA[Thu, 31 Oct 2013 05:42:52 +0000]]></pubDate><author><![CDATA[Patrick Wyatt]]></author><description><![CDATA[<p>Developing games is a full-time occupation, so it is no surprise that I&#8217;ve had less time for blogging as I&#8217;ve started creating a new game. After a two-year stint helping other folks publish their games I&#8217;m back to coding and game design full-time and having a wonderful time. But for those of you who have [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/stay-awhile-and-listen">Stay Awhile and Listen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></description><content><![CDATA[<p>Developing games is a full-time occupation, so it is no surprise that I&#8217;ve had less time for blogging as I&#8217;ve started creating a new game. After a two-year stint helping other folks publish their games I&#8217;m back to coding and game design full-time and having a wonderful time.</p>
<p>But for those of you who have enjoyed my blogging about the early years of Blizzard Entertainment and the development of Warcraft, StarCraft and Diablo, and want more, I&#8217;m glad to be able to share the news: there&#8217;s a book available today about those very subjects!</p>
<p>Back in January, 2011, an author named David Craddock contacted me to chat about my experiences in the game industry, and what caused Blizzard to go from an unassuming startup to the dominating presence it has today.</p>
<p>Over the past couple of years David interviewed me and many other folks who were there from the early years of Blizzard and Blizzard North, and his book provides an intimate look at their games and the people involved.</p>
<p>During those formative years of my career in the game industry &#8212; Blizzard was my first job coming out of college &#8212; I discovered joy and sorrow in large measures. I still have raw feelings from some events of those times, and I still look back with fondness on many others. This book is about our naivete and hopefulness as we undertook an adventure to reinvent the game industry.</p>
<p>I hope you&#8217;ll enjoy the book: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00G8UL474/?tag=codofhon-20">Stay Awhile and Listen: How Two Blizzards Unleashed Diablo and Forged a Video-Game Empire</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/stay-awhile-and-listen">Stay Awhile and Listen</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[Uh-oh: was the company site hacked?]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/uh-oh-was-the-company-site-hacked]]></link><pubDate><![CDATA[Thu, 09 May 2013 04:40:37 +0000]]></pubDate><author><![CDATA[Patrick Wyatt]]></author><description><![CDATA[<p>Anyone who runs a web site knows that they&#8217;re constantly under attack. You only have to look at your log files to know that hackers running site-scanners are constantly hitting your servers looking for unpatched vulnerabilities to exploit. One of the servers I wrote for Guild Wars 1 &#8212; named AcctHttpSrv &#8212; was designed to [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/uh-oh-was-the-company-site-hacked">Uh-oh: was the company site hacked?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></description><content><![CDATA[<p>Anyone who runs a web site knows that they&#8217;re constantly under attack. You only have to look at your log files to know that hackers running site-scanners are constantly hitting your servers looking for unpatched vulnerabilities to exploit.</p>
<p>One of the servers I wrote for Guild Wars 1 &#8212; named AcctHttpSrv &#8212; was designed to behave like a web server. When you received an email from the Guild Wars account management system and clicked on the link it contained, AcctHttpSrv would convert that click into a database transaction to update your account information. Pretty standard stuff.</p>
<p>For debugging purposes I configured AcctHttpSrv to log all unknown requests it received for later review. It turned out the number of errors logged was larger by far than the number of valid transactions. Peeking at the error log provided a view into an entirely different universe, a firsthand look at the dark side of the Internet, each line an exploit that had likely been successful on other sites in the past.</p>
<p>Just the other day one of my readers pointed out that <em>this</em> site started misbehaving: the articles RSS feed stopped functioning. Since I hadn&#8217;t logged in for several weeks it likely wasn&#8217;t a change I had made. My first guess was a new WordPress hack as there have been several recently, so I ran some security scans (nothing found) and rolled back the site to a previous backup, which fixed the bug. My thanks to Steven Y. for pointing out the problem.</p>
<p>So I thought I&#8217;d use the occasion share a story about a web deploy that went awry.</p>
<p>At a previous company I worked at the web team was getting ready to roll out a completely new game site. The old site was in need of a revamp, but rather than re-use the crufty and difficult-to-use web content-management system (CMS) that had been built by an external web agency our team chose a new CMS that would make it easy for non-developers to post game news and updates with no programming required.</p>
<p>The web team was under the gun to deliver the site on a deadline because the game&#8217;s platform and services were cross-linked with it, and consequently those services could not be rolled out until the main web site went live. Several missed deadlines, late nights, heroic efforts and so forth, but eventually the site content was ready.</p>
<p>The web team pushed the content to the servers and started forwarding traffic from old servers to new. We were all happy to see the results of their efforts live at last, with everything running smoothly.</p>
<p>Then one of the web developers made a startling announcement. &#8220;Greg&#8221; (not his real name) announced that he was seeing an &#8220;adult&#8221; image displayed on the site. Ack! We&#8217;ve only been live a few minutes and it has been hacked already?!?</p>
<p>The web team, operations team, and security team jump on the problem. Let&#8217;s verify this &#8212; RIGHT NOW!</p>
<p>Oddly, nobody besides Greg can reproduce the problem. Should we switch back to the old servers? Brazen it out and call it a feature?</p>
<p>While it wouldn&#8217;t be impossible for the site to be hacked, it would be challenging. See, we weren&#8217;t actually using the CMS yet &#8212; it wasn&#8217;t ready in time. We were actually hosting the entire site as static files. Instead of running the site on a smart web server capable of dynamically generating content, we ran the site on the equivalent of a dumb file server.</p>
<p>As we approached the deadline it became clear that, while the site&#8217;s content was complete, there were some CMS issues that prevented it from being deployed. But we HAD to deploy the site! So I hacked together a trivial solution which scraped all the web pages from a QA-test server and we posted those files on the public web server. For the technically inclined:</p>
<pre><code>wget --input-file list-of-urls-to-scrape.txt --mirror
</code></pre>
<p>Since we weren&#8217;t running a dynamic language on the web server, the attack surface was small enough that we could verify the configuration was correct pretty quickly. Hmmm&#8230; what are we missing; the clock is ticking!</p>
<p>After a few minutes, Greg sheepishly announced that he had discovered the problem. It turned out that the web browser he was using on his mobile phone (Opera) sometimes rendered pages incorrectly, leaving images from a previously viewed page visible while downloading a new page. Well &#8230; you can guess the kind of pages he was checking out at lunch just before the site was deployed.</p>
<p>I have to give him props, though. A lot of folks would not have said anything and we all would have been held in suspense for months. He owned up and saved us all a lot of grief, and we didn&#8217;t have to roll back to the old site. Problem solved!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/uh-oh-was-the-company-site-hacked">Uh-oh: was the company site hacked?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[The StarCraft path-finding hack]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/the-starcraft-path-finding-hack]]></link><pubDate><![CDATA[Wed, 20 Feb 2013 05:40:36 +0000]]></pubDate><author><![CDATA[Patrick Wyatt]]></author><description><![CDATA[<p>Game-unit path-finding is something that most players never notice until it doesn&#8217;t work quite right, and then that minor issue becomes a rage-inducing, end-of-the-world problem. During the development of StarCraft there were times when path-finding just didn&#8217;t work at all. As the development of StarCraft dragged on it seemed like it would never be done: [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/the-starcraft-path-finding-hack">The StarCraft path-finding hack</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></description><content><![CDATA[<p>Game-unit path-finding is something that most players never notice until it doesn&#8217;t work <em>quite right</em>, and then that minor issue becomes a rage-inducing, end-of-the-world problem. During the development of StarCraft there were times when path-finding just didn&#8217;t work <em>at all</em>.</p>
<p>As the development of StarCraft dragged on it seemed like it would never be done: the game was always two months from launch but never seemed to get any closer to the mythical ship date. &#8220;Fortunately&#8221; &#8212; and I use that term advisedly &#8212; Blizzard had previous experience shipping games late.</p>
<p>While we always had launch-date &#8220;goals&#8221; (though &#8220;wishes&#8221; might be a better term) we tried not to announce publicly until there was a good chance that the game would be ready at that point. Blizzard&#8217;s &#8220;when it&#8217;s done&#8221; policy for game launch was as much an admission that no one had any idea when we would finish as it was a commitment to releasing quality products.</p>
<p>In any event, towards the end of the project we had a set of problems that prevented launching. Like any game in the latter stages of the development process there were defects galore that needed to be found and repaired and the bug count still numbered in the thousands.</p>
<p>Many of those bugs were trivial, and needed only a little attention to fix. Too bad they weren&#8217;t all like that.</p>
<p>Others, like a multiplayer synchronization bug, would pop up and require dedicated attention from several members of the programming team &#8212; sometimes weeks of effort for a single problem. Other game developers have reported similar experiences with their sync bugs: <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/131503/1500_archers_on_a_288_network_.php?print=1">Ages of Empires</a> and <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/126022/Opinion_Synchronous_RTS_Engines_And_A_Tale_of_Desyncs.php">Supreme Commander</a>.</p>
<p>Some bugs were related to the development process itself. The Protoss Carrier regularly lagged behind other units because it had its own way of doing &#8230; everything. At some point in time the code for the Carrier was branched from the main game code and had diverged beyond any hope of re-integration. Consequently any time a feature was added for other units, it had to be re-implemented for the Carrier. And any time a bug was fixed for other units, a similar bug would later be found in the Carrier code too, only more devious and difficult to fix.</p>
<p>But the biggest thing holding back StarCraft was unit path-finding.</p>
<p>It wasn&#8217;t that the path-finding was totally broken; in most cases it worked quite well. But there were enough edge-cases that the game was un-shippable.</p>
<p>Game units would get stuck and stop on the battlefield. Often they would go through elaborate efforts to find paths, inching forward or looping around but not making progress, and sometimes getting wedged and unable to move further. Entire task forces would get bogged down in what looked like the afternoon commute.</p>
<p>The problem was frustrating for players, but also made the AI weak and consequently made it impossible to balance the missions, wasting design time.</p>
<p>Though I was never a top-tier RTS player, before the game launched I was good at the game because I discovered that Goliaths were overpowered to make up for their poor path-finding abilities. Because they were larger than other ground units they needed wider spaces for path-finding, and so by carefully shepherding Goliaths around obstacles I was able to bring their firepower to bear in crucial situations to overcome &#8220;macro&#8221; players who would otherwise tear me to shreds. Sadly my skills only lasted a short while until the Goliaths were rebalanced. <em>sigh</em></p>
<p>Early path-finding was rough &#8212; while there were well-chosen algorithms driving unit movement they were handicapped by some poor development decisions made during the course of the project.</p>
<h3>How did we get here?</h3>
<p>In an <a href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/tough-times-on-the-road-to-starcraft#path-finding">earlier article on this blog</a> I alluded to the path-finding difficulties. StarCraft was built on the Warcraft engine, which renders terrain-art using a tile-engine that&#8217;s optimized to draw 32&#215;32 pixel square tiles made of 16 8&#215;8 pixel square cells. I architected Warcraft this way because it had worked well for our Super Nintendo and Genesis titles. Those game consoles had hardware support for drawing 8&#215;8 cells, but the behavior was easy to emulate on a PC.</p>
<p>Because the camera perspective of Warcraft I and II were almost top-down, the edges of objects (forests, terrain, buildings) on game maps are either horizontal or vertical, so the render-engine&#8217;s representation of the world as a square tile-map is conducive to easy path-finding. In those games each 32&#215;32 tile was either passable or un-passable. I&#8217;ve shown a few of the <del datetime="2013-02-20T21:05:39+00:00">passable tiles</del> tile-edges in the image below in green. Some tiles appeared passable but actually were not; below you can see the barracks building artwork does not fill the <del datetime="2013-06-12T05:52:36+00:00">48&#215;48</del>96&#215;96 area it sits on completely, leaving two tiles that appear passable but actually are not (red).</p>
<div id="attachment_647" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Warcraft2.jpg" alt="Annotated Warcraft 2 screen captured show tile edges" width="640" height="480" class="size-full wp-image-647" srcset="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Warcraft2-300x225.jpg 300w, http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Warcraft2.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Warcraft 2 map with 32&#215;32 tiles</p></div>
<p>But along the way the development team switched StarCraft to isometric artwork to make the game more visually attractive (<a href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/starcraft-orcs-in-space-go-down-in-flames">details in previous post</a>). But the underlying terrain engine wasn&#8217;t re-engineered to use isometric tiles, only the artwork which was redrawn.</p>
<p>The new camera perspective looked great but in order for path-finding to work properly it was necessary to increase the resolution of the path-finding map: now each 8&#215;8 tile was either passable or un-passable, increasing the size of the path-finding map by a factor of 16. While this finer resolution enabled more units to be squeezed onto the map, it also meant that searching for a path around the map would require substantially more computational effort to search the larger pathing-space.</p>
<p>Path-finding was now more challenging because diagonal edges drawn in the artwork split many of the square tiles unevenly, making it hard to determine whether a tile should be passable or not. Ensuring that all tiles were correctly marked required painstaking effort.</p>
<p>And the StarCraft map editor was horribly difficult to write because of the many edge-cases necessitated by laying down diagonal shapes onto a square tile-map. Writing the specialized &#8220;tile-fixup&#8221; code necessitated months programming time.</p>
<p>Unlike Diablo, which used an isometric tile-rendering engine, the StarCraft development team kept the old engine even as new problems with the approach continued to be discovered week by week.</p>
<p>This image shows how a bridge was made up of 8&#215;8 cells; several are shown in green. The almost isometric perspective of the artwork unevenly slices through the cells, leading to a stair-stepped edge along each side of the bridge, as you can see where the red line cuts each tile into an irregular shape.</p>
<div id="attachment_646" style="width: 650px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Starcraft.jpg" alt="Annotated StarCraft screen captured show tile edges" width="640" height="480" class="size-full wp-image-646" srcset="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Starcraft-300x225.jpg 300w, http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Starcraft.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><p class="wp-caption-text">StarCraft map with 8&#215;8 cells</p></div>
<p>Because the project was always two months from launch it was inconceivable that there was enough time to re-engineer the terrain engine to make path-finding easier, so the path-finding code just had to be made to work. To handle all the tricky edge-cases, the pathing code exploded into a gigantic state-machine which encoded all sorts of specialized &#8220;get me out of here&#8221; hacks.</p>
<h3>Rush hour</h3>
<p>If there was any one major problem with path-finding it was that harvesting units (Terran SCV, Zerg drone, Protoss probe) would get jammed up trying to harvest crystals or vespene gas (hereafter &#8220;minerals&#8221;), and they would grind to a halt. While a player was busy managing an attack or constructing a secondary, the harvesters back at the home base would jam up, halting the flow of minerals into the treasury. When next the player looked up the entire build-queue would have collapsed due to lack of cash.</p>
<p>The basic problem with resource-gathering is that players want to max-out the number of harvesters working on each mineral deposit to maximize their cash flow. Those harvesters are commuting between the minerals and their base so they&#8217;re constantly running headlong into other harvesters traveling in the opposite direction. Given enough harvesters in a small space it&#8217;s entirely possible that some get jammed in and are unable to move until the mineral deposit is mined out.</p>
<h3>How do we get out of here?</h3>
<p>I either volunteered or was asked to look into the problem; I just can&#8217;t remember after all this time. After studying the path-finding code extensively I realized that there was no way I was smart enough to just &#8220;fix the problem&#8221;. So I came up with a dirty hack instead.</p>
<p>While programmers can become obsessed with finding the most pure, abstract, clean, even sublime solution to a problem, there are times in a project when a few sacrifices have to be made. If they&#8217;re done well no one notices the evil compromises that had to be made, as is true for the hacks written up by Brandon Sheffield in his article <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/4111/dirty_coding_tricks.php">Dirty Coding Tricks</a>.</p>
<p>My idea was simple: whenever harvesters are on their way to get minerals, or when they&#8217;re on the way back carrying those minerals, they ignore collisions with <del datetime="2013-02-20T21:26:54+00:00">other harvesters in the same state</del> other units. By eliminating the inter-unit collision code for the harvesters there is never a rush-hour commute to get jammed up, and harvesters operate efficiently.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s possible to notice this behavior by selecting a large group of harvesters who are working a plot of crystals and telling them to halt. They immediately spread out to find tiles that aren&#8217;t occupied by other harvesters.</p>
<p>The behavior is obvious if you look, but hidden in plain sight &#8212; it doesn&#8217;t rise to the level of conscious awareness, though professional-level players and map-makers/modders do notice.</p>
<p>In short, it just works, which is the best kind of hack.</p>
<p>And while there was a lot more work required to finish the game, that hack was what enabled us to launch without massive and time-consuming re-engineering.</p>
<p>The development team was able to work around some of the other path-finding problems and just plain ignore the rest, though the Protoss Dragoon in particular ended up with a bad reputation because, as the largest ground-unit, it frequently failed to path well.</p>
<p>The final result was that path-finding was good enough, and we all learned a hard lesson about hope and wishful thinking as scheduling tools.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/the-starcraft-path-finding-hack">The StarCraft path-finding hack</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[Whose bug is this anyway?!?]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/whose-bug-is-this-anyway]]></link><pubDate><![CDATA[Tue, 18 Dec 2012 17:56:21 +0000]]></pubDate><author><![CDATA[Patrick Wyatt]]></author><description><![CDATA[<p>At a certain point in every programmer&#8217;s career we each find a bug that seems impossible because the code is right, dammit! So it must be the operating system, the tools or the computer that&#8217;s causing the problem. Right?!? Today&#8217;s story is about some of those bugs I&#8217;ve discovered in my career. This bug is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/whose-bug-is-this-anyway">Whose bug is this anyway?!?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></description><content><![CDATA[<p>At a certain point in every programmer&#8217;s career we each find a bug that seems impossible because the code is right, dammit! So it <em>must</em> be the operating system, the tools or the computer that&#8217;s causing the problem. Right?!?</p>
<p>Today&#8217;s story is about some of those bugs I&#8217;ve discovered in my career.</p>
<h3>This bug is Microsoft&#8217;s fault&#8230; or not</h3>
<p>Several months after the launch of Diablo in late 1995, the StarCraft team put on the hustle and started working extra long hours to get the game done. Since the game was &#8220;only two months from launch&#8221; it seemed to make sense to work more hours every day (and some weekends too). There was much to do because, even though the team started with the Warcraft II game engine almost every system needed rework. All of the scheduling estimates were willfully wrong (my own included), so this extra effort kept on for over a year.</p>
<p>I wasn&#8217;t originally part of the StarCraft dev team, but after Diablo launched, when it became clear that StarCraft needed more &#8220;resources&#8221; (AKA people), I joined the effort. Because I came aboard late I didn&#8217;t have a defined role, so instead I just &#8220;used the force&#8221; to figure out what needed to happen to move the project forward (<a href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/tough-times-on-the-road-to-starcraft">more details in a previous post on this blog</a>).</p>
<p>I got to write fun features like implementing parts of the computer AI, which was largely developed by Bob Fitch. One was a system to determine the best place to create &#8220;strong-points&#8221; &#8212; places that AI players would gather units for defense and staging areas for attacks. I was fortunate because there were already well-designed APIs that I could query to learn which map areas were joined together by the path-finding algorithm and where concentrations of enemy units were located in order to select good strong-points, as it would otherwise be embarrassing to fortify positions that could be trivially bypassed by opponents.</p>
<p>I re-implemented some components like the &#8220;fog of war&#8221; system I had written for previous incarnations of the &#8216;Craft series. StarCraft deserved to have a better fog-of-war system than its predecessor, Warcraft II, with finer resolution in the fog-map, and we meant to include line-of-sight visibility calculations so that units on higher terrain would be invisible to those on lower terrain, greatly increasing the tactical complexity of the game: when you can&#8217;t see what the enemy is doing the game is far more complicated. Similarly, units around a corner would be out of sight and couldn&#8217;t be detected.</p>
<p>The new fog of war was the most enjoyable part of the project for me as I needed to do some quick learning to make the system functional and fast. Earlier efforts by another programmer were graphically displeasing and moreover, ran so slowly as to be unworkable. I learned about <a href="http://lodev.org/cgtutor/filtering.html">texture filtering algorithms</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gouraud_shading">Gouraud shading</a>, and wrote the best x386 assembly language of my career &#8212; a skill now almost unnecessary for modern game development. Like many others I hope that StarCraft is eventually open-sourced, in my case so I can look with fondness on my coding efforts, though perhaps my memories are better than seeing the actual code!</p>
<p>But my greatest contribution to the StarCraft code was fixing defects. With so many folks working extreme hours writing brand new code the entire development process was haunted by bugs: two steps forward, one step back. While most of the team coded new features, I spent my days hunting down the problems identified by our Quality Assurance (QA) test team.</p>
<p>The trick for effective bug-fixing is to discover how to reliably reproduce a problem. Once you know how to replicate a bug it&#8217;s possible to discover why the bug occurs, and then it&#8217;s often straightforward to fix. Unfortunately reproducing a &#8220;will o&#8217; the wisp&#8221; bug that only occasionally deigns to show up can take days or weeks of work. Even worse is that it is difficult or impossible to determine beforehand how long a bug will take to fix, so long hours investigating were the order of the day. My terse status updates to the team were along the lines of &#8220;yeah, still looking for it&#8221;. I&#8217;d sit down in the morning and basically spend all day cracking on, sometimes fixing hundreds of issues, but many times fixing none.</p>
<p>One day I came across some code that wasn&#8217;t working: it was supposed to choose a behavior for a game unit based on the unit&#8217;s class (&#8220;harvesting unit&#8221;, &#8220;flying unit&#8221;, &#8220;ground unit&#8221;, etc.) and state (&#8220;active&#8221;, &#8220;disabled&#8221;, &#8220;under attack&#8221;, &#8220;busy&#8221;, &#8220;idle&#8221;, etc.). I don&#8217;t remember the specifics after so many years, but something along the lines of this:</p>
<pre><code>if (UnitIsHarvester(unit))
    return X;

if (UnitIsFlying(unit)) {
    if (UnitCannotAttack(unit))
        return Z;
    return Y;
}

... many more lines

if (! UnitIsHarvester(unit))    // "!" means "not"
    return Q;

return R;   &lt;&lt;&lt; BUG: this code is never reached!
</code></pre>
<p>After staring at the problem for too many hours I guessed it might be a compiler bug, so I looked at the assembly language code.</p>
<p>For the non-programmers out there, compilers are tools that take the code that programmers write and convert it into &#8220;machine code&#8221;, which are the individual instructions executed by the CPU.</p>
<pre><code>// Add two numbers in C, C#, C++ or Java
A = B + C

; Add two numbers in 80386 assembly
mov     eax, [B]    ; move B into a register
add     eax, [C]    ; add C to that register
mov     [A], eax    ; save results into A
</code></pre>
<p>After looking at the assembly code I concluded that the compiler was generating the wrong results, and sent a bug report off to Microsoft &#8212; the first compiler bug report I&#8217;d ever submitted. And I received a response in short order, which in retrospect is surprising: considering that Microsoft wrote the most popular compiler in the world it&#8217;s hard to imagine that my bug report got any attention at all, much less a quick reply!</p>
<p>You can probably guess &#8212; it wasn&#8217;t a bug, there was a trivial error I had been staring at all along but didn&#8217;t notice. In my exhaustion &#8212; weeks of 12+ hour days &#8212; I had failed to see that it was impossible for the code to work properly. It&#8217;s not possible for a unit to be neither &#8220;a harvester&#8221; nor &#8220;not a harvester&#8221;. The Microsoft tester who wrote back politely explained my mistake. I felt crushed and humiliated at the time, only slightly mitigated by the knowledge that the bug was now fixable.</p>
<p>Incidentally, this is one of the reasons that crunch time is a failed development methodology, as I&#8217;ve mentioned in past posts on this blog; developers get tired and start making stupid mistakes. It&#8217;s far more effective to work reasonable hours, go home, have a life, and come back fresh the next day.</p>
<p>When I started ArenaNet with two of my friends the &#8220;no crunch&#8221; philosophy was a cornerstone of our development effort, and one of the reasons we didn&#8217;t buy foozball tables and arcade machines for the office. Work, go home at a reasonable time, come back fresh!</p>
<h3>This bug is actually Microsoft&#8217;s fault</h3>
<p>Several years later, while working on Guild Wars, we discovered a catastrophic bug that caused game servers to crash on startup. Unfortunately, this bug didn&#8217;t occur in the &#8220;dev&#8221; (&#8220;development&#8221;) branch that the programming team used for everyday work, nor did it occur in the &#8220;stage&#8221; (&#8220;staging&#8221;) branch used by the game testers for final verification, it only occurred in the &#8220;live&#8221; branch which our players used to play the game. We had &#8220;pushed&#8221; a new build out to end-users, and now none of them could play the game! WTF!</p>
<p>Having thousands of angry players amps up the pressure to get that kind of problem fixed quickly. Fortunately we were able to &#8220;roll back&#8221; the code changes and restore the previous version of the code in short order, but now we needed to understand how we broke the build. Like many problems in programming, it turned out that several issues taken together conspired to cause the bug.</p>
<p>There was a compiler bug in Microsoft Visual Studio 6 (MSVC6), which we used to build the game. Yes! Not our fault! Well, except that our testing failed to uncover the problem. Whoops.</p>
<p>Under certain circumstances the compiler would generate incorrect results when processing templates. What are templates? <a href="http://yosefk.com/c++fqa/templates.html">They&#8217;re useful, but they&#8217;ll blow your mind; read this if you dare</a>.</p>
<p>C++ is a complex programming language so it is no surprise that compilers that implement the language have their own bugs. In fact the C++ language is far more complicated than other mainstream languages, <a href="http://cpprocks.com/cpp-ruby-coffeescript-language-complexity/">as shown in this article that visualizes the complexity of C++ compared to the Ruby language</a>. Ruby is a complex and fully-featured language, but as the diagram shows C++ is twice as complex, so we would expect it to have twice as many bugs, all other things being equal.</p>
<p>When we researched the compiler bug it turned out to be one that we already knew about, and that had already fixed by the Microsoft dev team in MSVC6 Service Pack 5 (SP5). In fact all of the programmers had already upgraded to SP5. Sadly, though we had each updated our work computers we neglected to upgrade the build server, which is the computer that gathers the code, artwork, game maps and other assets and turns them into a playable game. So while the game would run perfectly on each programmers&#8217; computer, it would fail horribly when built by the build server. But only in the live branch!</p>
<p>Why only in live? Hmmm&#8230; Well, ideally all branches (dev, stage, live) would be identical to eliminate the opportunity for bugs just like this one, but in fact there were a number of differences. For a start we disabled many debugging capabilities for the live branch that were used by the programming and test teams. These capabilities could be used to create gold and items, or spawn monsters, or even crash the game.</p>
<p>We wanted to make sure that the ArenaNet and NCsoft staff didn&#8217;t have access to cheat functions because we wanted to create a level playing field for all players. Many MMO companies have had to fire folks who abused their godlike &#8220;GM&#8221; powers so we thought to eliminate that problem by removing capability.</p>
<p>A further change was to eliminate some of the &#8220;sanity checking&#8221; code that&#8217;s used to validate that the game is functioning properly. This type of code, known as asserts or assertions by programmers, is used to ensure that the game state is proper and correct before and after a computation. These assertions come with a cost, however: each additional check that has to be performed takes time; with enough assertions embedded in the code the game can run quite slowly. We had decided to disable assertions in the live code to reduce the CPU utilization of the game servers, but this had the unintended consequence of causing the C++ compiler to generate the incorrect results which led to the game crash. A program that doesn&#8217;t run uses a lot less CPU, but that wasn&#8217;t actually the desired result.</p>
<p>The bug was easily fixed by upgrading the build server, but in the end we decided to leave assertions enabled even for live builds. The anticipated cost-savings in CPU utilization (or more correctly, the anticipated savings from being able to purchase fewer computers in the future) were lost due to the programming effort required to identify the bug, so we felt it better to avoid similar issues in future.</p>
<p>Lesson learned: everyone, programmers and build servers alike, should be running the same version of the tools!</p>
<h3>Your computer is broken</h3>
<p>After my experience reporting a non-bug to the folks at Microsoft, I was notably more shy about suggesting that bugs might be caused by anything other than the code I or one of my teammates wrote.</p>
<p>During the development of Guild Wars (GW) I had occasion to review many bug reports sent in from players&#8217; computers. As GW players may remember, in the (hopefully unlikely) event that the game crashed it would offer to send the bug report back to our &#8220;lab&#8221; for analysis. When we received those bug reports we triaged to determine who should handle each report, but of course bugs come in all manner of shapes and sizes and some don&#8217;t have a clear owner, so several of us would take turns at fixing these bugs.</p>
<p>Periodically we&#8217;d come across bugs that defied belief and we&#8217;d be left scratching our heads. While it wasn&#8217;t impossible for the bugs to occur, and we could construct hypothetically plausible explanations that didn&#8217;t involve redefining the space-time continuum, they just &#8220;shouldn&#8217;t&#8221; have occurred. It was possible they could be memory corruption or thread race issues, but given the information we had it just seemed unlikely.</p>
<p>Mike O&#8217;Brien, one of the co-founders and a crack programmer, eventually came up with the idea that they were related to computer hardware failures rather than programming failures. More importantly he had the bright idea for how to test that hypothesis, which is the mark of an excellent scientist.</p>
<p>He wrote a module (&#8220;OsStress&#8221;) which would allocate a block of memory, perform calculations in that memory block, and then compare the results of the calculation to a table of known answers. He encoded this stress-test into the main game loop so that the computer would perform this verification step about 30-50 times per second.</p>
<p>On a properly functioning computer this stress test should never fail, but surprisingly we discovered that on about 1% of the computers being used to play Guild Wars it did fail! One percent might not sound like a big deal, but when one million gamers play the game on any given day that means 10,000 would have at least one crash bug. Our programming team could spend weeks researching the bugs for just one day at that rate!</p>
<p>When the stress test failed Guild Wars would alert the user by closing the game and launching a web browser to a <a href="http://www.guildwars.com/support/en-hardwarefailure.php">Hardware Failure page</a> which detailed the several common causes that we discovered over time:</p>
<ul>
<li>Memory failure: in the early days of the IBM PC, when hardware failures were more common, computers used to have <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAM_parity">&#8220;RAM parity bits&#8221;</a> so that in the event a portion of the memory failed the computer hardware would be able to detect the problem and halt computation, but parity RAM fell out of favor in the early &#8217;90s. Some computers use <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ECC_memory">&#8220;Error Correcting Code&#8221; (ECC) memory</a>, but because of the additional cost it is more commonly found on servers rather than desktop computers. Related articles: <a href="http://news.cnet.com/8301-30685_3-10370026-264.html">Google: Computer memory flakier than expected</a> and <a href="http://www.sc.edu/news/newsarticle.php?nid=5371">doctoral student unravels ‘tin whisker’ mystery</a>.</li>
<p></p>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overclock">Overclocking</a>: while less common these days, many gamers used to buy lower <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clock_rate">clock rate</a> &#8212; and hence less expensive &#8212; CPUs for their computers, and would then increase the clock frequency to improve performance. Overclocking a CPU from 1.8 GHz to 1.9 GHz might work for one particular chip but not another. I&#8217;ve overclocked computers myself without experiencing an increase in crash-rate, but some users ratchet up the clock frequency so high as to cause spectacular crashes as the signals bouncing around inside the CPU don&#8217;t show up at the right time or place.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Inadequate power supply: many gamers purchase new computers every few years, but purchase new graphics cards more frequently. Graphics cards are an inexpensive system upgrade which generate remarkable improvements in game graphics quality. During the era when Guild Wars was released many of these newer graphics cards had substantially higher power needs than their predecessors, and in some cases a computer power supply was unable to provide enough power when the computer was &#8220;under load&#8221;, as happens when playing games.</li>
<p></p>
<li>Overheating: Computers don&#8217;t much like to be hot and malfunction more frequently in those conditions, which is why computer datacenters are usually cooled to 68-72F (20-22C). Computer games try to maximize video frame-rate to create better visual fidelity; that increase in frame-rate can cause computer temperatures to spike beyond the tolerable range, causing game crashes.</li>
<p>
</ul>
<p>In college I had an external hard-drive on my Mac that would frequently malfunction during spring and summer when it got too hot. I purchased a six-foot SCSI cable that was long enough to reach from my desk to the mini-fridge (nicknamed Julio), and kept the hard-drive in the fridge year round. No further problems!</p>
<p>Once the Guild Wars tech support team was alerted to the overheating issue they had success fixing many otherwise intractable crash bugs. When they received certain types of crash reports they encouraged players to create more air flow by relocating furniture, adding external fans, or just blowing out the accumulated dust that builds up over years, and that solved many problems.</p>
<p>While implementing the computer stress test solution seems beyond the call of duty it had a huge payoff: we were able to identify computers that were generating bogus bug reports and ignore their crashes. When millions of people play a game in any given week, even a low defect rate can result in more bug reports than the programming team can field. By focusing our efforts on the bugs that were actually our fault the programming team was able to spend time creating features that players wanted instead of triaging unfixable bugs.</p>
<h3>Ever more bugs</h3>
<p>I don&#8217;t think that we&#8217;ll ever reach a stage where computer programs don&#8217;t have bugs &#8212; the increase in the expectations from users is rising faster than the technical abilities of programmers. The Warcraft 1 code base was approximately 200,000 lines of code (including in-house tools), whereas Guild Wars 1 eventually grew to 6.5 million lines of code (including tools). Even if it&#8217;s possible to write fewer bugs per line of code, the vast increase in the number of lines of code means it is difficult to reduce the total bug count. But we&#8217;ll keep trying.</p>
<p>To close out this post I wanted to share one of my favorite tongue-in-cheek quotes from Bob Fitch, who I worked with back in my Blizzard days. He posited that &#8220;all programs can be optimized, and all programs have bugs; therefore all programs can be optimized to one line that doesn&#8217;t work.&#8221; And that&#8217;s why we have bugs.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog/whose-bug-is-this-anyway">Whose bug is this anyway?!?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.codeofhonor.com/blog">Code Of Honor</a>.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[Title]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.example.org]]></link><pubDate/><author><![CDATA[Auth]]></author><description><![CDATA[Description	]]></description><content><![CDATA[COntent]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[Title2]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.example2.org]]></link><pubDate/><author><![CDATA[Auth2]]></author><description><![CDATA[Desc 2]]></description><content><![CDATA[Content 2]]></content></item><item><title><![CDATA[Title3]]></title><link><![CDATA[http://www.example3.org]]></link><pubDate/><author><![CDATA[Auth3]]></author><description><![CDATA[dfsdfsdfdsfsdfsdfsdfsd]]></description><content><![CDATA[fsdfsdfsdfsdfsdfdsf]]></content></item></channel></news-list>